Fairfield School Records, 1668-1952 Ms 14
Fairfield Museum and History Center
Fairfield School Records, 1668-1952
Ms 14
Fairfield Museum and History Center
2.5 Linear feet 5 boxes 500 items
This collection contains material from various schools and school districts in Fairfield including workbooks, teacher certifications, enrollments, pamphlets, yearbooks, budgets and meeting minutes.
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Biographical/Historical note
Elizabeth Schenck places the building of the first school house in Fairfield around 1640. First mention of school in the Fairfield town minutes occurs on February 10, 1662:
The towne orders that Srian Sqire and Rod Turney goe to every family in the towne and make tryall what scollars are to be payable scollars to the schoolmaster and bring in a list of their names to the secretary that ther may be a rate made to pay the scollmaster.
This collection contains documentation for several districts: Banks South, Burrs, Deerfield, First Located School Society, Green's Farms, Greenfield School Society, Hull's Farms, Jennings' Woods, Middle School, Millplaine (Mill Plain), Mill River, Southport and Stratfield North.
Private schools have also proliferated in Fairfield. Advertisements for Mill Allen's Seminary, Miss Braden's School, Grail School and Mr. Brewer's Home and A School for Boys give only a small sample of the many private schools in Fairfield before 1935. Further information about Fairfield's school history can be found in The History of Fairfield, Fairfield County, Connecticut by Elizabeth Hubbell Schenk, New York, 1889.
The Fairfield Academy was organized in 1802, opened in 1804, and closed about 1884, although the building was rented or given to several teachers to be used as a private school after that. For a detailed history, see Elizabeth L. Child's An Old Landmark, Being an Account of the Fairfield Academy, 1927.
Scope and Contents note
The collection is divided into six boxes. The first three hold school records, public and private, organized in alphabetical order by name of school. Included are lists of students, school records, ledgers, records of school meetings, bills and receipts, teachers' record books, teacher certifications, advertising brochures, deeds and petitions, certificates of merit and other miscellaneous items.
Box III holds documents concerning Fairfield Academy, including the original record book (1802-1844) which contains the list of original subscribers, charters, registry and transfer of shares, and proprietors' meeting minutes. Folders B-G hold miscellaneous memorabilia, correspondence, bills, teachers' record books, report cards, etc. Folder H contains collected material concerning the restoration of the Academy building, 1927-1929.
Boxes IV and V hold school work books (1777-1883), school papers and miscellaneous pamphlets concerning Fairfield schools.
Related Archival Materials note
See also Ms B48--Fairfield School Collection, 1891-1992
Fairfield Academy (Fairfield, Conn.) .; Fairfield(Conn.); Penmanship; School attendance; School facilities--Connecticut--Design and construction--Finance--Planning.; School notebooks; Schools--Connecticut.; Teachers--Certification--Connecticut.
- Fairfield School Records-Box I, Box I
  - Misc. private school items, Folder A; 3 items
    - Miss Allen's Female Seminary advertisement, 1825
    - Miss Braden's School, brochure and letter
  - Banks School District, Folder B; 3 items
    - Banks South school district: List of expenses and students paid to Horace Smith; record books, 5 May 1846, 1857 & 1858
    - Banks North School District bill, 1877
  - Burrs District, Folder C; 40 items
    - Notices of school district meetings, 1869-1874, 1877, 1879-1880, 1884-1885, n.d.
    - Records of school meetings, 1862, 1899, n.d.
    - Receipts, 1861-1875
    - Treasurer's reports, 1883-1884, 1884-1885, 1878-1879
    - School bill, 1855-1856
  - Burrs District (cont'd), Folder D; 7 items
    - School record books, Rufus B. Jennings, teacher, 1853-1859, 1856, 1859 ,1861, 1864
  - Deerfield and Burrs Districts, Folder E; 2 items
    - School record book, Adaline Allfred, teacher
    - School record book, Rufus B. Jennings, teacher, 1854-1855
  - Easton school district: Easton Academy, Folder F; 11 items
    - Receipts, 1856, n.d.
    - Notice of meeting, 1856
    - School record, 1856
    - Letter from James Ensigner, Principal of Easton Academy, 1846
  - Fairfield schools' earliest and miscellaneous records, Folder G; 13 items
    - Copy of Fairfield school record, 1668
    - School accounts, 1791, 1792
    - Teachers' records (lists of students, bills, etc), 1801, 1807, 1809, 1812, 1818, ca, 1880
    - Receipt for dividend on school funds, 1831
    - Certification of Timothy N. Banks, 1841
  - First Located School Society (Fairfield School Society), Folder H; 7 items
    - Certification for Mr. James M. Sherman, teacher, 1818
    - Certification for teachers of the Mill River district, 1820
    - Bill, 1830
    - Land deed forms, 1830
    - Deed to Oliver Perry, 1849
    - Deed to Gordon Perry, 1851
  - First Located School Society (cont.), 1 item
    - Ledger, school records, 1805-1855
- Fairfield School Records-Box IA, Box IA
  - Greenfield School Society, Folder J; 1 item
    - Ledger-financial records, 1799-1839
  - Greenfield School District, Folder K; 6 items
    - Letter from James Beach to William Fanton
    - Circular from Superintendent of Common Schools, Hartford, 1847
    - Taxpayer list, 1852
    - Teacher certification, 1856
    - Petitions for school locations, 1801, 1806
  - Greenfield School District, Folder L; 2 items
    - Greenfield School register, 1871-1872
    - Exercise program, 1898
  - Green's Farms School Society, Folder M; 2 items
    - Teacher certification, 1807
    - Notice of meeting, 1837
  - Home and School for Boys, Folder N; 5 items
    - Receipt, 1900
    - School brochures, n.d.
  - Hulls Farms District, Folder O; 5 items
    - School bill, 1807
    - Teacher's record, 1808
    - List of students, 1823
    - Teacher's certification, 1835
    - Notice of school district meeting, 1838
  - Jennings' Woods (Fairfield Woods) School District, Folder P; 10 items
    - Receipt, 1812
    - Teacher's certification, 1840
    - George A. Merwin, letter and teachers' contracts, 1894
    - Bound ledger containing teachers' lists and records of school meetings, 1850, 1856-1893
    - Promissory note, 1885
    - Petition in favor of Miss Amelia Fiebel, teacher, 1890
    - Student report card, n.d.
  - Middle School and Mill Plain School Districts, Folder Q; 3 items
    - Report of petition to extend school house in Middle School district
    - Certification of school visit, Mill Plain
    - Mill Plain district Alfred Perry Committee account book, 1823-1824
  - Mill River School District, Southport, Folder R; 3 items
    - Clerk's book (minutes of school meetings) and loose material from book, 1827-1866
  - Account, 1792; Folder R1
- Fairfield School Records-Box II, Box II
  - Southport School District, Folder A; 7 items
    - Minutes of school district meeting, 1840
    - Copy of authorization for collection of school taxes, 1854
    - Page 11 of tax list, 1859
    - Petition to Board of Education, 1886
    - Sasquanaug Association--presentation of flag to school, 1893
    - Finance (?) committee report, ca. 1893
    - Pencilled note, n.d.
  - Southport School District (cont.), Folder B; 1 item
    - Treasurer's ledger, 1856-1911
  - Southport School District (cont.), Folder C; 1 item
    - Ledger, records of school district meetings, 1867-1893
  - Stratfield, North School District, Folder D; 1 item
    - Bill for repair of school house, 1857
  - Westport, Weston & North Fairfield Schools, Folder E; 6 items
    - Teacher's report, Weston, 1799, 1806
    - Green's Farms Academy brochure and report card
    - Staples Free School, Easton, 1795-1881
    - Photocopy graduation program, 1939
  - Non-local bills, Folder F; 2 items
    - N. Brewster to Cornelius Van Hoarn, Florida, 1794
    - H. W. Lyon's Collegiate Institute, N. Y. for Henry L. Mills, Jr., 1874
  - Certificates of Merit, Folder G; 23 items
    - Ann B. Coley, 1847
    - William C. Morehouse, 1871; 3 items
    - John G. Nichols, m.d.
    - Helen Page, 1895; 3 items
    - Alexander Parker, 1825
    - W. S. Pickett, n.d.; 2 items
    - Elizabeth Scofield, 1831; 3 items
    - Sally Wakemen, 1821
    - Reward of merit, blank
  - Record book, Fairfield High School Class of 1918 & loose papers, 1914-1918; Folder H; 10 items
  - Fairfield High School report cards, 1873, 1875; Folder I
- Fairfield Academy, Box III
  - Record book, 1802-1804; Folder A; Includes a list of the original subscribers, copy of the Act of Incorporation, records of proprietor's meetings, copy of the charter and registry and transfer of shares. At the back of the book is a circa late 18th or early 19th century copy of lists of persons with thier sums annexed in the town of Fairfield who suffered in the late war between Great Britain and America and proprietors of the land south of Lake Erie quit claimed to said proprietors with others by the General Assembly of the State of Connecticut in their session May 1792.
    - Record book, 1802-1884
  - Miscellaneous items, Folder B; 6 items
    - Meeting minutes, 1804
    - Academy rules, circa 1804
    - Awards of merit, n.d.
    - Quit-claim deed to St. Paul's Church, 1854-1855
    - Autograph book to "Nettie", 1889
  - Tuition, Folder C; 21 items
    - Summary of quarterly bills, 1810-1811
    - General statement, n.d.
    - Miscellaneous bills, 1821, 1830, 1877, 1897-1899, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous bills and accounts, 1803, 1805, 1806, 1808, 1810, 1830, 1831, 1868, n.d.; Folder D; 10 items
  - Teachers' record books, 1853-1854; Folder E; 3 items
  - Student activities, reports and papers, Folder F; 20 items
    - Report cards-George Merwin, John Woods, Fred Burr
    - Copy book, n.d.
    - Programs, 1894-1899; 7 items
    - Rules, 1885
    - Field day records, 1894
    - Photostat and transcript of letter from "Isaac", 1852
  - Correspondence and documents, 1904-1923; Folder G; 17 items
    - Annual report, 1904
    - Correspondence, Samuel C. Morehouse to Dr. S. C. Garlick, 1904
    - Documents and correspondence concerning boundary between St. Paul's Church and Fairfield Academy, 1922-1923; 14 items
  - Restoration of Fairfield Academy, 1927-1929; Folder H; 55 items
    - The Old Academy Fund bank statements, 10 items
    - The Old Academy Fund cancelled checks, 11 items
    - The Old Academy Fund bank book
    - Pledge cards and envelope, 9 items
    - Correspondence to E. Child, 1926, 1927; 2 items
    - Committee minutes, 8 items
    - List (possibly of committee members), 8 items
    - Itemized bills from Tomlinson and Hawley, 9 items
    - Summary sheet of bills
    - Newspaper clippings, 2 items
    - Brochure, 1927
  - Record books, Folder I; 2 items
    - Book listing contributors to restoration
    - Unidentified book, possibly visitor's log, n. d.
  - The Old Academy by Elizabeth L. Child, 1927; Folder J
  - Reminscence of Fairfield Academy, 1898; Folder K
- School Workbooks--Mathematics, Box IV
  - Amanda Bennett's cyphering book, 1828; Folder A
  - George Hawkin's writing book, 1831; Folder B
  - Miss Mariett Lyon's sum book, 1836-1837; Folder C
  - Miss Emily Post, 1823; Folder D
  - Jesse L. Sanford's cyphering book, 1805-1806; Folder E
  - Jesse L. Sanford's cyphering book, 1809-1810; Folder F
  - John Thorp, 1777; Folder G
  - unidentified, 1802-1804; Folder H
  - unidentified, 1817-1819; Folder I
  - Geometry, 1821; Folder J
  - unidentified, 1824-1825; Folder K
  - Elijah Peet, 1814; Folder L
- School Workbooks, Box V
  - Calvin Seeley surveying book, 1821; Folder A
  - Surveying books, n.d.; Folder B
  - Surveying books, n.d.; Folder C
  - Penmanship books, Folder D
    - George A. Banks, 1872
    - Medora Beach, n.d.
  - Edward Treadwell penmanship, circa 1831; Folder E
  - E. Banks, Maple Grove Academy, Green's Farms, double-entry book-keeping, 1861; Folder F
  - Practice ledgers, 1845, 1869, 1883; Folder G; 3 items
  - E. S. Tredwell history lecture notes, 1837; Folder H
  - Notes-literature, German, physiology, n.d.; Folder I
  - School papers, Folder J
    - A. E. Banks, copied essay, 1876
    - George A Banks, essay, 1875
    - George A. Banks, penmanship, 1876
    - Banks, mathematics, n.d.
    - J. D. Bradley, teacher's advice, n.d.
    - Marcus Burr, essay, 1851
    - B. B. Jennings, mathematics, n.d.
    - Penmanship scraps, n.d.
  - Pamplets, Folder K; 3 items
    - The Schools of Greenfield through Two Centuries by George Merwin, 1925
    - Reminiscences of Fairfield Academy, 1935; 2 items